In the late 1990s I was working for, I was a student at Princeton doing a PhD and I
was employed by the CCA who were organizing a big international competition that
were looking at sort of ideas of urban ideas always located in a different city.
they imagined it like a sort of Olympiad.
So every four years they'd choose a different city
with a very contested, ideologically loaded site.
They'd have a competition, get some architectural responses,
and then four years later they'd go on to the next one.
In fact, the competition was stillborn,
or it only existed only ever once, in 1999 in New York.
And I was involved in the running of that competition
all the way through to the selection of the competitors.
than the presentations.
It was called the International Federation for the Design of Cities.
But it was an interesting moment.
It was a moment of sort of largesse too,
because before all of the kind of economic crashes,
that the CCA had money then, and they were spending it.
And so money was no object.
So we really went after an interesting cast of characters.
We had publications and exhibitions.
and more pertinently for you and us,
is that Cedric was one of those five competitors.
And he was really chosen as a kind of left-field candidate.
The other candidates were Eisenman, Morphosis,
Ben Van Berkel, Jesse Reiser.
So pretty much drawn from a certain aesthetic camp.
and they chose Cedric just as a sort of counter to that.
But immediately after they selected him,
they were clearly terrified of him
because of what he sort of represented and who he was.
So there was a lot of sort of knee trembling, I seem to remember.
So I, peculiarly as a sort of young PhD student,
I'd find myself on these...
I was merely a stenographer, basically.
I was writing out minutes of jury meetings with Rafael Maneo and Frank Gehry, Liz
Diller, Erata Isazaki, you know, the great and the good.
And I remember we had these sort of really terrifying meetings in the Four Seasons
restaurant, which was then owned by Phyllis Lambert.
So as the heiress of Seagram, the woman who designed Seagram,
again, a rather odd experience,
entering Seagram with the woman who designed it
and then being seated.
She would then order off the menu.
The menu itself was as big as a... I'm digressing here.
It was a sort of A0 document.
And I'd be studying this menu, sort of hiding behind it,
And the other side of me would be Arata Isozaki, Frank Gehry, Rafa Mineo, Liz
Diller.
And Phyllis would say, oh, I just want steamed vegetables, actually.
I don't need to eat anything.
I'm not very hungry.
And then Isozaki, who was next to her, would say, actually, you know,
being very deferential in Japanese, actually, steamed vegetables would be perfect
for me as well.
And then Frank Gehry was next to Isozaki and said, you know, I've just come on a
red-eye flight.
Steamed vegetables is fine.
So then I was next, and I was like,
this is the first time I'd ever been to Four Seasons.
And you're looking at this amazing menu.
So I said, I can't lose this opportunity.
So I said, I'll have the white truffle risotto
followed by the roast bison.
And I just remember the Dean of Princeton
really kicking me under the table, boot.
So that was the sort of beginning of that whole experience for me.
The great and the good were very clearly anxious
about what to do with Cedric.
It was a sort of problem, you know, what are we going to do with Cedric?
He's about to arrive, he's about to come, you know,
how are we going to deal with him?
And I was basically assigned the task of being his sort of minder
or his sort of agent.
And so a couple of days later when he did arrive,
I had to pick him up and escort him around,
look after him a bit in New York, speak and just chat to him.
And whereas all of the other contestants had huge sort of entourage of assistants
and people and baggage and just an amazing amount of stuff, Cedric just sort of
walked in by himself, wanted to see the site.
You know, the way he sort of sketched in the site and documented things was
incredibly low-tech and minimalist.
And then, but it was just, you know, it was a great experience for me encountering
him, but I was only given that responsibility, that role, because of my Englishness.
It was just like, you, English guy, speak to him because you can talk that language.
Us, Americans or whatever, will just not get it.
get it and it became much more apparent when he presented at the end of the
competition
when again all of these other firms had a huge number of people, big projections,
digital
projections, slide projections, boards, models, all a kind of paraphernalia of a big
architectural
presentation and Cedric I remember just had 26 A4 sheets of paper with very
simple pencil sketches on that we basically bulldog clipped to a board in
a grid which produced sort of howls of derision from all of the other
competitors at how sort of low-tech and sort of somehow insubstantial this was.
This is an architect famous for not building, famous for developing ideas,
famous for questioning whether you needed a building at all. That was his
great sort of response to any given brief, to deny the the incentive to
have a building at all. So he was perfect there and and true to form he didn't
really produce a building. He did some very kind of precise bit of sort of incisions
within an
urban grain. It was a kind of autopsy basically, a kind of Dr. Nicholas Toip style
Rembrandt
unpicking of her body, whereas the others were all bells, all whistles, all singing
and dancing,
early days of digital parametricism,
Cedric just pulled out a few little slithers
of some existing buildings in and around the site
and then did some characteristic sketches
with Xerox montages of the view behind an interior space,
people sitting in chairs looking out over a view.
But as a corpus of material,
it did look rather unimpressive when you saw it,
but then we scanned all that material
and exhibited it in Grand Central Station
with all the other competitors.
And we backlit all of the drawings
three metres by 25 metres
in the middle of Grand Central Station.
And when all of the parametricism suddenly dulled down,
given that scale,
suddenly a Cedric drawing, a pencil drawing,
scanned from a sheet of white A4 paper,
three metres high, 20 metres wide,
looked astonishing.
and actually you could really not only see a graphic but you could see an idea
and you could see the real clarity of a piece of thinking
so that is my kind of
primal Cedric Price moment
and it came kind of full circle again when if it began with this rather painful
dinner it ended when that summer, the summer afterwards
I came back to London to see my family, he took me out
to lunch at St John
to say thanks for the help I'd given him.
And we had a lunch.
I never have been drunker,
iller.
I think I'm still slightly drunk now.
Ten years, fourteen years later.
It began in the sort of late morning
and ended in the late afternoon.
And I remember I had to actually go out for dinner
that evening with some other friends
and I crawled into the restaurant
where I was meeting the friends
and I was wasted. Now that I'm doing this book and we're transcribing all of the
lectures,
where you see Cedric give a lecture where he drinks during the course of the
lecture,
in many ways he starts off, his natural state is drunk and alcohol somehow sobers
him up. He
gets sort of somehow more coherent and more precise the drunker he gets. So he,
So exactly the same was in St John. By the end we were talking in absolute clarity
with each other.
But maybe this is a sort of characteristic of our own drunkenness.
Through my work now on the AA files and editing work I'm doing on the AA, as a sort
of side project I'm increasingly looking at the idea of the AA.
and the way the AA has represented itself through media,
through the printed form, through the broadcast form,
through all forms of graphics.
And Cedric is absolutely fundamental to that,
not least because you first see him at the AA
just like any other AA tutor,
as a kind of figure doing a desk crit,
leaning over a student,
pointing out certain aspects in a drawing.
So you see those early pictures of him in the late 1950s, early 60s,
at the AA in a studio setting.
Then increasingly when the Boyarskian revolution comes through the AA,
he's pulled out of the studio and placed in front of an audience
and he starts to give these characteristically
sort of mellifluous and performative and compelling lectures
as a sort of media figure
and he then starts to become aware of his own mediarisation,
that he knows he's part of this,
that the Dennis Crompton Archigramme are all starting to film lectures then.
So the video camera, as much as the audience, is in front of them.
And then Boyarsky does this move with launching the AA's own TV station as TVAA.
And the very first thing he has within TVAA
is he uses Cedric as host of his own programme,
looking at architectural magazines.
So it's media, Cedric, commenting on media, the published form,
as the cornerstone of a new vision, a new curriculum for the AA.
So Cedric is very much like one of those evolutionary diagrams
of a kind of ape becoming Homo sapiens,
from the conventional tutor to this utterly mediated figure.
And I guess the perfect moment of that
is the famous picture of Cedric taking a picture of the photographer taking his
picture.
This endless sort of mise en abyme, sort of Las Meninas kind of moment
of him utterly in control of his own public mediated persona.
So I think before one even discusses any of his ideas, any of his architecture,
the idea of him is so fundamental.
you know, just simply the silhouette of him is fundamental to how he sort of
resonated.
I mean, when I was younger, I remember I used to live about a mile or so away from
the AA,
just off Charlotte Street, and I'd sit in my flat working on my thesis or whatever.
And I'd often see Cedric as he walked from the AA to, or from Storrs Street to the
RIBA.
I guess he was going to the RIBA.
and my street happened to be on that sort of the crossover between those two
locations
and I'd spot him the second he sort of walked around the corner
because you saw the sheepskin jacket, you saw the collar and the striped shirt,
you saw the cigar smoke.
So, I mean, it is something of a cliché to talk about sort of cartoonish
characteristics of him
But it was so obvious, you know,
that he was very much a kind of figure
enwrapped by his own kind of caricature.
His most significant project is himself, is Cedric Price.
And that's something, again, we're having to be really careful of
when we're doing this book.
Not only because of what people understand Cedric to be,
the cliched reading is of a kind of Englishman
with a certain sartorial presence
who will always challenge the validity
or the necessity of a building
and somehow will be a prelude to a sort of avant-gardism
will somehow reimagine everything
change all the rules of the game
but actually as we're discovering with the book
that we have to be mindful of the seriousness of him.
I think it would be a mistake to present him as a comic figure.
He's full of laughs and full of jokes, but he's deadly serious.
And as I'm discovering with the book,
and partly I discovered at the CCA in New York when I met him,
is how pragmatic he is and how he's in many ways grounded
not in a sort of artful or architectural tradition,
but an engineering tradition.
He's got a real sort of scientific or pseudo-scientific mindset,
and it's revealed by the fact that his sort of pals and his acquaintances
and his patrons and his clients were drawn from those sort of big bodies
of English engineering traditions, of the kind of British rail,
of the kind of English aerospace technologies,
of heavy infrastructural backers and heavy infrastructural projects,
that it wasn't the kind of frou-frou flippancies of aesthetics, of just decoration,
it was the real guts of a kind of urban or national morphology.
Cedric's commitment to the idea of the architect as an enabler
rather than perhaps an esthete or a form-giver
or someone in control of aesthetics
is in many ways his greatest legacy
and is the thing that we should remember most about him.
And it's the thing that's counter to our vision of the architect now,
as someone so much in command of a kind of visual and formal and material language,
where his own expertise was in just the kind of fundamental questions
of what architecture can provide, what it can actually enable.
what would be listed in his passport under occupation.
I think he would list architect.
I don't think he would see another word for it.
But it isn't a Latin understanding of the architect.
It isn't a sort of Vitruvian understanding
or a Palladian understanding of the...
Albertian understanding of the architect.
I always think of it as like a sort of architect as an oil rigger.
There's a sort of hard hat approach,
but it's someone who's just at the absolute source of something.
The rig, I think, is a more aposite sort of vehicle,
a sort of Trojan horse, I think, for him,
rather than the temple or the church or the monument,
more heroic vehicles of architectural language.
So the aviary, I always see it.
Colehouse famously calls the aviary a cage,
but I think I see it more as this...
I don't see the netting.
I simply see the structure, you know, I see it as a sort of rig in a way,
parked on the side of a park.
I think Price was committed to the idea of the ordinary.
I don't think he was interested in the extraordinary.
And I think that is the misreading of Price now,
that he is always imagining a fantastical world,
that it's avant-garde and it questions everything.
I think he's very committed to the idea of the everyday
and the things that we like
just like his rituals of smoking and drinking
and eating and entertaining and laughing
and a certain English sensibility
I think he's also committed to an everyday idea of what's around us
that he isn't thinking there's some kind of panacea
that'll cure everything in the form of some architectural silhouette.
He's using all of the elements that are provided by the everyday,
by the ordinary, and just looking at them more closely,
just sort of rearranging them a little bit
or heightening them or dampening down others.
The key relevance of Cedric today would be,
firstly, as a man who ultimately expressed himself
through the spoken word,
that our understanding now of the architect is a largely mute one,
that the architect draws or the architect simply exists or performs
so that the silhouette, in a sort of El Croquis way,
one sees the profile of the architect
as if that is the register of everything that they do.
You get these big black-and-white cover images of El Croquis or whatever,
and one understands Foster, one understands Zaha,
as if that's everything.
and they never really say anything.
So the architecture becomes increasingly mute.
Cedric was someone fundamentally based on talking
and what he was actually saying.
So the man behind the lectern, I think,
is an important kind of legacy
that one should try and return to, I think,
try and pull architects out from the shadows
and force them in front of an audience like that,
talking not simply behind images,
not simply behind the PowerPoint of slides of their own magnum opus,
but about ideas.
Cedric was just always presenting ideas more than anything else.
So I think that would be the ultimate legacy and the benchmark
or the kind of carrot that one should place in front of today's architects
or aspiring architects, what they imagine an architectural career to be.
Not least also the fact that he had one foot in the school
as much as it was in the office.
that I think his commitment to architectural education or the institution, I think,
is fundamental to any architect.
It's not that the overlaps between the two, I think, are crucial.
So in many ways he's paradigmatic in that sense.